♪You crossed the sea of ​​stars and came with light♪
♪เธอข้ามผ่านหมู่ดวงดาว มาพร้อมกับแสงสว่าง♪
♪My heart is like the dust, and I couldn't bear to stain the hemline♪
♪หัวใจฉันเปรียบเหมือนฝุ่น ไม่อยากแปดเปื้อนกระโปรงของเธอ♪
♪To love in a different way, the fireworks are in the stars' good graces♪
♪ความรักที่ไม่เหมือนใคร ดอกไม้ไฟที่ดวงดาวยังชายตามอง♪
♪I turn around and realize that my heart is empty ♪
♪หันกลับมาจึงเข้าใจ ดวงใจได้ขาดหายไป♪
♪I miss the overflowing galaxy surging into the sea♪
♪ความคิดถึงท่วมท้นจักรวาล เอ่อล้นจนเต็มท้องทะเล♪
♪Even the fireworks desire to give the stars a future♪
♪ดอกไม้ไฟอยากเป็นที่พึ่งพิงให้ดวงดาว♪
♪As long as you are around♪
♪ขอเพียงแค่มีเธออยู่♪
♪Even the fireworks fear to bloom♪
♪ดอกไม้ไฟกลัวจะสว่างแล้วดับสูญ♪
♪Looking at you, the light in your eyes dimmed♪
♪มองดูนัยน์ตาของเธอ แสงไฟค่อย ๆ เลือนหาย♪
♪I laughed at myself and that I deserve it ♪
♪ทำได้แต่สมน้ำหน้าตัวเอง♪
♪My heart skips a beat, but I'm afraid I'm not worthy of the future that you desire♪
♪ฉันใจสั่น♪
=You Are My Glory=
=ดุจดวงดาวเกียรติยศ=
=Episode 20=
=ตอนที่ 20=
So my answers truly don't matter anymore?
มันไม่มีความหมายแล้วจริง ๆ เหรอ
Why did you write
ทำไมนายต้องเขียน
those letters to me?
จดหมายพวกนั้นด้วย
Why did you want
ทำไมต้องตอบคำถาม
to answer my questions?
ที่ฉันเคยถามด้วย
Do you regret it?
นายเสียดายเหรอ
Because I was so stupid,
เพราะความโง่ของฉันในตอนนั้น
and you were touched?
มันทำให้นายประทับใจงั้นเหรอ
I don't want this.
ฉันไม่ได้ต้องการแบบนี้
Yu Tu.
อวี๋ถู
Did I
ฉันทำเรื่อง
do anything stupid?
ที่มันโง่มากเลยใช่ไหม
Of late,
ช่วงหลายวันนั้น
I've been writing till late every day.
ฉันเขียนจดหมายถึงดึกทุกคืน
But I never felt tired.
แต่ก็ไม่เคยรู้สึกเหนื่อยเลย
I got smug.
ฉันพอใจ
My expectations ran high.
และตื่นเต้นมาก
I thought you'd be pleased to know.
เพราะคิดว่าเมื่อเธอได้อ่านคงจะดีใจ
Jingjing,
จิงจิง
to think like this,
ที่คิดแบบนี้
has my IQ level
เพราะไอคิวของฉัน
fallen into a negative?
มันลดลงถึงขั้นติดลบใช่ไหม
All the stupid things I did all my life
เรื่องโง่ ๆ ที่ฉันเคยทำในชีวิต
are because of you.
ฉันทำเพื่อเธอคนเดียวเท่านั้น
I couldn't think of another way.
ฉันคิดวิธีอื่นไม่ออกแล้ว
It's not because I only regretted
ไม่ใช่เพราะเจอแชทเก่าแล้ว
after reading the chat history.
ถึงคิดเสียใจ
I've regretted it a long time ago.
ฉันเสียใจมานานแล้ว
I just dared not admit it.
เพียงแค่ไม่กล้ายอมรับ
Then, I went on a business trip.
ตอนหลังฉันไปทำงานต่างเมือง
I spent over a month in the desert.
อยู่ในทะเลทรายเดือนกว่า
I thought I was still struggling.
ฉันคิดว่าฉันคงทุรนทุราย
But one day I realized,
แต่มีวันหนึ่งที่ฉันพบว่า
I spent too little time struggling.
แค่เวลาทุรนทุรายฉันยังมีน้อยเหลือเกิน
Most of the time, I was thinking
เวลาส่วนใหญ่ฉันเอาแต่คิดว่า
of how to get back what I lost.
จะทำให้เธอกลับคืนมาได้ยังไง
I even...
บางครั้ง
started blaming you.
ฉันก็คิดโทษเธอ
I blamed you
โทษเธอว่า
for asking me so soon.
ทำไมถึงมาถามฉันเร็วแบบนี้
If you had given me a little more time,
ถ้าให้เวลาฉันอีกสักหน่อย
I would've surrendered to myself.
ฉันคงยอมแพ้กับตัวเอง
It'd be better
ถ้าตอนนั้น
if I had asked you instead.
ให้ฉันเป็นคนถามเธอก็คงดี
Ask what?
ถามอะไร
Well...
ถามว่า
Would you like to be with me?
เธอเป็นแฟนกับฉันได้ไหม
Jingjing.
จิงจิง
Would you like to be with me?
เธอยินดีคบกับฉันไหม
♪Pulling the sleeves♪
♪ฉันฝันเห็นแสงดาวระยิบระยับ บนชายแขนเสื้อ♪
♪A white top covering the thin shoulders♪
♪ชุดสีขาว ปกคลุมหัวไหล่อันซูบเซียว♪
♪I have seen the wounds healed with each passing year♪
♪ฉันเห็นกาลเวลาเยียวยาบาดแผลได้♪
I guess I would.
ยินดีนิดหน่อย
♪There will always be people♪
♪อย่างไรก็มีคนไล่ตามชั่วฟ้าดินสลาย♪
But to say this,
แต่ถึงจะพูดอย่างนั้น
it breaks my heart.
ฉันก็ยังโกรธอยู่ดี
♪The bustling intersection♪
♪ท่ามกลางทางแยกผู้คนพลุกพล่าน♪
♪Looking back all of a sudden under the dim light♪
♪แสงไฟริบหรี่ เหลียวหลังมองไป♪
♪I loved♪
♪เคยรักเธอ มองไปยังดาวทอประกายบนฟากฟ้า นัยน์ตาที่สงบนิ่ง♪
♪And I loved the universe in your heart♪
♪ก็เคยรักเธอ ในใจฉันเธอคือทุกอย่าง ในจักรวาล♪
♪Time does not stop♪
♪กาลเวลาไม่เคยหยุดรอ เก็บซ่อนความเสียใจในสิ่งที่ทำไปตลอดเวลา♪
I'm sorry.
ขอโทษนะ
♪The wind passes by the tall buildings with no one awaiting it♪
♪ลมพัดผ่านตึกสูง ไม่มีใครเฝ้ารออีกต่อไป♪
I'm sorry.
ขอโทษ ขอโทษ
I don't want to like someone
ฉันไม่อยากได้คนที่ชอบฉัน
more than he likes me.
น้อยกว่าที่ฉันชอบเขา
I don't accept this.
เหตุผลนี้ฟังไม่ขึ้น
I don't like you less than you do to me.
ฉันไม่ได้ชอบเธอน้อยกว่า
Yes, you do.
น้อยกว่า
You said we were not meant for each other.
นายบอกว่าเราไม่เหมาะสมกัน
That was because...
นั่นเป็นเพราะ
I came up with a few
ฉันคิดถึงเหตุผล
lame excuses.
ที่คนเขาชอบพูดกัน
Such as...
อย่างเช่น
my income.
เรื่องรายได้
what I could give you,
ฉันจะให้อะไรเธอได้บ้าง
and if I'd have time
ฉันจะมีเวลา
to take good care of you.
ดูแลเธอหรือเปล่า
I also don't have time for you.
ฉันก็ไม่มีเวลาดูแลนายเหมือนกัน
When you truly like someone
การชอบใครสักคน
You'll be reckless.
มันห้ามใจไม่อยู่
You won't hesitate.
ไม่คิดลังเล ดิ้นรน
You won't overthink.
ไม่คิดมากมายขนาดนั้น
I'm probably different from you.
งั้นฉันคงไม่เหมือนเธอ
I thought too much.
ฉันคิดมากเหลือเกิน
I've been thinking about the rest of my life.
คิดแทบทั้งชีวิต
But you thought less than me.
ยังไงนายก็ชอบน้อยกว่าอยู่ดี
How about this?
เอาอย่างนี้ดีไหม
You give me a calculation method,
เธอบอกวิธีคำนวณฉันมา
show me how you calculate,
ว่าน้อยหรือมากคิดยังไง
then I will fix it.
แล้วฉันจะชดเชยให้เธอเอง
You won't even tell me your formula,
แค่สูตรคำนวณเธอคงไม่อุบไว้
will you?
ไม่ยอมบอกฉันหรอกนะ
(Formula?)
(สูตรคำนวณ)
You're bullying me again.
นายแกล้งฉันอีกแล้ว
♪I've dreamed of traveling around the planet♪
♪ฉันก็เคยคิดฝันท่องไปตามดวงดาว♪
I was wrong.
ฉันผิดเอง
♪Seeing the galaxy pass through the clouds♪
♪ผ่านมวลเมฆ ดูทางช้างเผือกที่หลั่งไหล♪
I didn't agree.
ฉันยังไม่ตอบตกลงนะ
I know.
ฉันรู้
I'm getting cold.
ฉันหนาว
Let's get in the car.
งั้นขึ้นรถกันเถอะ
But you sit in front, okay?
แต่เธอนั่งเบาะหน้าได้ไหม
You'll be my navigator and show me...
ช่วยฉันดูแผนที่นำทางหน่อย
the way to your home.
ทางไปอี๋ซิง
I really don't know.
ฉันไม่รู้จริง ๆ
I need to fill the car up.
ฉันจะเติมน้ำมันหน่อย
Jingjing,
จิงจิง
where do you live?
บ้านเธออยู่ที่ไหน
Ready to go.
เตรียมออกเดินทาง
82 kilometers.
ระยะทางแปดสิบสองกิโลเมตร
ETA
ใช้เวลาประมาณ
in one hour and 31 minutes.
หนึ่งชั่วโมงสามสิบเอ็ดนาที
Jingjing.
จิงจิง
I...
ฉัน
I'm home?
ถึงบ้านแล้ว
Thanks for the ride.
ฉันลงล่ะ
Well, here I go.
ฉันเข้าบ้านก่อนนะ
When will you go back to Shanghai?
เธอจะกลับเซี่ยงไฮ้เมื่อไหร่
Xiao Zhu said,
เสี่ยวจูบอกว่า
you'd return to Shanghai on the fourth day,
วันชูซื่อเธอต้องกลับเซี่ยงไฮ้ [*ชูซื่อ : วันชิวสี่ สี่วันนับจากวันตรุษจีน]
and then travel for filming on the fifth.
แล้วชูอู่ต้องไปถ่ายหนังที่ต่างเมือง [*ชูอู่ : วันชิวโหงว ห้าวันนับจากวันตรุษจีน]
Is that right?
ถูกต้องไหม
Pretty much it.
ก็ประมาณนั้นแหละ
I see.
เข้าใจแล้ว
Happy New Year to you.
สุขสันต์วันตรุษจีนนะ
Happy New Year.
สุขสันต์วันตรุษจีน
Then how will you go home?
แล้วนายจะกลับยังไง
I'll walk.
เดินไปน่ะ
My place isn't far from here.
บ้านฉันอยู่ไม่ไกลมาก
So when you get...
งั้นนายถึง...
Yes.
ได้
I won't reply to you.
แต่ฉันไม่ตอบนายหรอกนะ
Great.
โอเค
Good night.
กู๊ดไนท์
Jingjing!
พี่
Did I hear it right?
หูผมดีจริง ๆ
She's home!
กลับมาแล้วเหรอ
I'll help you with your suitcase.
พี่ ผมช่วยยกกระเป๋า
You're home at last.
มาถึงสักทีนะ
It's about time.
ดูเวลาก็คิดว่าน่าจะถึงแล้ว
Be careful.
ระวังนะ
Oh, dear.
ดูซิลูกคนนี้
Why didn't you call us as soon as you got home?
กลับมาถึงบ้านก็ไม่โทรบอก
You didn't even ring the doorbell.
แถมยังไม่กดกริ่ง
You even had to drag that big thing by yourself?
กระเป๋าใหญ่นั่นลากเข้ามาเองเหรอ
Where's your driver?
คนขับรถลูกล่ะ
Let's go.
เข้าบ้านเถอะ
Come on, mom. I'm hungry.
แม่ เข้าบ้านเถอะ หนูหิวแล้ว
Gladly, I've left you some food.
เตรียมข้าวไว้ให้ลูกแล้ว
Here she is!
กลับมาแล้ว กลับมาแล้ว
You guys play for a while
พวกเธอเล่นกันไปก่อนนะ
while I'll get you dinner.
แม่จะไปตักข้าวมาให้
Happy New Year!
สุขสันต์วันตรุษจีนค่ะ
West wind.
ไพ่ตะวันตก
It's your turn.
ตาลูกแล้ว
Here.
นี่
Bingo!
ชนะแล้ว
You again!
คุณอีกแล้ว
West wind.
ไพ่ตะวันตก
No, no.
ไม่เอา ไม่เอา
Come on.
มา มา มา
Don't you...
อย่าสิลูก
Is that another discard?
จะทิ้งไหม
Don't discard this!
อย่าทิ้งอันนี้สิ
Isn't that...
เดี๋ยวก็
you are waiting for the tile?
น็อคแล้ว
- Why? - Discard this.
- ทำไมคะ - ทิ้งอันนี้
Hurry up!
เร็วหน่อยสิ
Let me...
งั้นหนู ๆ
This one.
อันนี้
One character.
ไพ่หนึ่งหมื่น
Good.
โอเค
Another character.
ไพ่หนึ่งหมื่นอีกแล้ว
(I am home.)
(ฉันถึงบ้านแล้ว)
Draw a tile.
จั่ว จั่ว จั่ว
What?
มีอะไรคะ
Dad, come on.
พ่อ มาเล่นแทนหนูเลย
Come on, come on.
มาเลยพ่อ มาเลย
Take it from her. Go ahead.
พี่เขย เร็วหน่อย
What a squanderer she is.
ดูซิยัยเด็กคนนี้
For me, it's a nine.
ฉัน เก้า
You quit?
ไม่เล่นแล้วเหรอ
(It took him half an hour to get home.)
(เดินตั้งครึ่งชั่วโมงกว่าจะถึงบ้าน)
(I wonder)
(หรือว่าบ้านเขา)
(if he still lives there,)
(ยังอยู่ที่เดิมนะ)
(in the old town.)
(ที่เขตเมืองเก่าน่ะ)
Jingjing!
พี่
New Year is not a time to spend on your phone.
ตรุษจีนจะมัวเล่นมือถืออยู่ทำไม
Let's play another round.
มาเล่นไพ่กับผมดีกว่า
Play what?
ไพ่อะไร
A round of mahjong, of course.
พวกเราจะเล่นไพ่นกกระจอก
Just for a little while.
เล่นกันสักแป๊บ
We don't mind you playing badly.
พวกผมไม่ว่าหรอกถ้าพี่เล่นห่วย
Come on, Jingjing.
มาเร็ว พี่
Just a little while.
เล่นด้วยกัน มาสิ
Come on.
นะ นะ นะ
Let's go.
มาสิ
Okay, but just once.
แค่ตาเดียวนะ
Clear the table!
เคลียร์โต๊ะเร็ว
Hurry up, Jingjing.
พี่ มาเร็วสิพี่
I'm coming.
มาแล้ว
Come on, let's play.
พี่ รีบมาเล่นด้วยกัน
(Qiao Jingjing)
(ฉันถึงบ้านแล้ว)
I knew there's someone at the door.
ก็ได้ยินอยู่ว่าหน้าประตูมีเสียง
Why don't you come in?
มาถึงแล้วทำไมไม่เข้าบ้านล่ะลูก
I told you not to wait for me.
บอกแล้วไงว่าไม่ต้องรอผม
It's New Year's Day.
คืนวันตรุษจีน
We'd be worried sick
ดึกป่านนี้ลูกยังไม่ถึงบ้าน
if you were not home by now.
พ่อกับแม่จะไม่เป็นห่วงได้ยังไง
Where did you go?
ไปไหนมา
Are you alright?
ไม่เป็นไรใช่ไหม
I am.
ไม่เป็นไรครับ
Mom.
แม่
Really, I'm fine.
ไม่เป็นไรจริง ๆ
Time for bed now.
รีบนอนเถอะครับ
He's asleep.
พ่อหลับแล้ว
So should you.
ลูกไปนอนเถอะ
Wake up.
ตื่นได้แล้ว
What?
มีอะไร
Yu Tu is home.
อวี๋ถูกลับมาแล้ว
Is he?
กลับมาแล้วเหรอ
Then I'm going to bed.
งั้นผมไปนอนล่ะ
Oh no, you don't.
จะนอนทำไม
What?
มีอะไร
We have to talk.
ฉันคุยกับคุณอยู่นะ
Yeah, what is it?
โอเค ว่ามา
Last time, he came to tell me
คราวก่อนลูกบอกฉันว่า
that he liked a girl.
เขาชอบผู้หญิงคนหนึ่ง
She's kind of pretty,
หน้าตาดี
but she's no caretaker.
แต่เทคแคร์คนไม่เป็น
I thought,
ฉันก็คิดอยู่นะ
there aren't many young women
ผู้หญิงสมัยนี้
who can take care of their partners nowadays.
มีสักกี่คนที่เทคแคร์คนเป็น
Yeah.
ใช่
Caring women like you
แบบที่ดูแลคนอื่นเป็นอย่างคุณ
are increasingly rare.
มีน้อยเสียยิ่งกว่าน้อย
Don't interrupt.
อย่าพูดแทรกสิ
This is serious.
ฉันกำลังพูดอยู่
Look at our son.
คุณดูลูกเรา
He hardly confides in us.
น้อยครั้งมากที่จะบอกเรื่องในใจให้เรารู้
I think,
ฉันว่านะ
he surely really likes her.
ลูกเราต้องชอบผู้หญิงคนนั้นจริง ๆ
He doesn't give a damn
ส่วนเรื่องเทคแคร์เป็นหรือเปล่า
if she can take care of him.
ไม่เห็นจะสลักสำคัญอะไร
Right?
จริงไหม
The thing is,
ประเด็นคือ
what's gotten into him today.
วันนี้ลูกเราเป็นขนาดนี้
I feel a little down seeing him.
ฉันไม่สบายใจเลย
What's making you down?
คุณไม่สบายใจเรื่องอะไร
You should've seen him,
เมื่อกี้คุณไม่เห็นเหรอ
looking all preoccupied
สภาพตอนลูกเรากลับมาถึงบ้าน
when he got here.
ใจลอยแบบนั้น
I have no idea
ไม่รู้ผู้หญิงคนนั้น
what she did
มีดีสักแค่ไหน
to him.
ถึงทำให้ลูกเราหลงได้ขนาดนี้
Ever since he was a kid,
อวี๋ถูลูกเรา
our Yu Tu
แต่ไหนแต่ไร
had heaps of girls
มีแต่สาว ๆ ตามจีบ
going after him.
เป็นขบวนรถไฟ
He didn't have to hit on one.
ลูกเราเคยต้องวิ่งตามจีบใครที่ไหน
She had him go out all New Year's Day,
วันตรุษจีนยังจะตามลูกออกไป
and he spent the day out
ไปอยู่ข้างนอกทั้งวัน
till so late.
แถมยังกลับดึก
Do you know what this means?
แบบนี้เรียกว่าอะไร
It's insensibility.
เรียกว่าไม่รู้มารยาท
It's fine if she's no caretaker,
เทคแคร์คนไม่เป็นไม่ใช่เรื่องใหญ่
but if she's insensible,
แต่ไม่รู้มารยาท
how will they get along in the future?
อนาคตจะอยู่ด้วยกันยังไง
You dozed off again.
หลับอีกแล้วเหรอ
No, I'm listening.
เปล่า ผมฟังอยู่
What did you listen to?
ฟังว่ายังไง
Don't bluff me!
คุณ พูดมาสิ
Yu Tu's girlfriend, right?
แฟนของอวี๋ถู
What do you know?
เป็นยังไง เป็นยังไง
Hey, you.
ผมว่าคุณน่ะ
Don't waste your breath, okay?
อย่าเสียแรงเปล่าเลยนะ
I'm his mother.
ฉันเป็นแม่นะ
It has to concern me.
ก็ต้องเป็นห่วงลูกสิ
What if she were not fond of him to begin with?
เกิดสาวเจ้าเขาไม่ได้ชอบอวี๋ถูล่ะ
Our relatives are coming over tomorrow.
พรุ่งนี้ญาติจะมาเยี่ยมพวกเรา
I have to get some rest.
ผมต้องไปนอนแล้ว
Stupid old man.
ตาแก่บ้า
You're his father, okay?
เป็นพ่อจริง ๆ หรือเปล่า
Big brother!
พี่
You're early.
มาแต่หัววันเลย
Come on in.
รีบมาน่ะ
Sister-in-law.
อาซ้อ
You've brought so many gifts.
เอาของอะไรมาตั้งเยอะตั้งแยะ
Happy Lunar New Year, Aunty!
น้าครับ สุขสันต์วันตรุษจีนครับ
Happy New Year.
สุขสันต์วันตรุษจีนจ้ะ
Yu Tu,
อวี๋ถู อวี๋ถู
have you wished them?
ทักทายญาติหรือยัง
Uncle.
อาเขย
Happy New Year.
สุขสันต์วันตรุษจีนครับ
Here, have some.
อะ กินสิ
Thank you.
ขอบคุณมากพี่
It's okay. I can do it myself.
ไม่เป็นไร ฉันทำเองได้
How's it going?
พี่เป็นไงบ้าง สบายดีไหม
Great.
พอได้อยู่
(Are you awake?)
(ตื่นหรือยัง)
(There's a)
(แถวบ้านฉัน)
(popular tofu store in my neighborhood.)
(มีร้านขายเต้าฮวยชื่อดังในอี๋ซิงอยู่เจ้าหนึ่ง)
(Would you like some?)
(เธออยากกินไหม)
Jingjing.
จิงจิง
Are you awake?
ตื่นหรือยัง
We're going to grandma's
อีกเดี๋ยวเราต้องไป
in a moment.
บ้านยายแล้วนะลูก
Yes!
ตื่นแล้วค่ะ
Sit down.
ไปนั่งเร็ว
Put it here.
วางตรงนี้
What a sumptuous breakfast today.
วันนี้ของกินเต็มไปหมด
There's so much.
เยอะจริง ๆ
Have some greens.
กินผักหน่อย
Come on, let's have a toast.
มา ๆ พวกเรามาดื่มกัน
Sure!
ได้
Cheers.
หมดแก้ว
Happy New Year!
สุขสันต์วันตรุษจีน
Wait up, will you?
ไม่รอกันเลย
This one's delicious.
อันนี้อร่อยนะ
It comes in many flavors.
มีให้เลือกตั้งหลายรส
Yu Tu,
พี่
you want the original
พี่จะเอารสดั้งเดิม
or white peach oats?
หรือจะเอาซีเรียลรสพีช
This one.
เอาอันนี้แล้วกัน
It's best to dine at home, you know.
กินในบ้านสบายกว่าเยอะ
Yeah.
ใช่
Come.
มา
Please, enjoy.
ไม่ต้องเกรงใจนะ กินเยอะ ๆ
Tell me if I'm
ดูซิว่าฝีมือฉัน
getting better at this.
ดีขึ้นกว่าเดิมไหม
Try this.
ลองชิมอันนี้
Sister-in-law, you are good at cooking this dish.
จานนี้อาซ้อทำอร่อยจังเลย
It's well fried.
อันนี้ก็ทอดดี
Would you like some more?
กินเยอะ ๆ นะ
Here, take more.
กินเยอะ ๆ เลย
Here, try this.
มา ๆ ลองชิมอันนี้
Eat more.
กินเยอะ ๆ
You too.
ตัวเองก็กินด้วยสิ
Don't just greet.
เอามัวแต่ดูแลคนอื่น
Eat up.
กินเลย
Okay.
โอเค
Don't just drink.
อย่าเอาแต่ดื่มสิ
Eat. It's so well-cooked.
- กินสิ - ฝีมือดีจริง ๆ
Yu Tu,
พี่
are you in love?
พี่มีแฟนแล้วใช่ไหม
You've been checking the phone all morning.
ดูโทรศัพท์แต่เช้า
Look at you.
ดูสภาพแล้ว
Looks like she gives you the cold shoulder.
ถูกแฟนเมินใส่มาใช่ไหม
You're so uncool.
พี่นี่ไม่เอาไหนเลย
You waste our genes.
เสียกรรมพันธุ์ตระกูลเราหมด
Now,
ผมน่ะ
if I send a text to a girl,
ส่งวีแชทหาสาว ๆ
it only takes seconds for her to reply to me.
ไม่กี่วิก็ตอบกลับแล้ว
You don't believe me?
ไม่เชื่อเหรอ
I'll show you.
เดี๋ยวส่งให้ดู
Here.
มา
Here, here.
มา มา มา
Come on, cheers.
มา ดื่ม
Sister-in-law.
ซ้อใหญ่
Have a great year ahead.
เหลือกินเหลือใช้ทุกปีนะ
Thanks.
ขอบคุณ
It's just a warm-up.
คนเก่งต้องสำเร็จจากเรื่องเล็ก ๆ
(Mi: Looks delicious. Yiyi: So sumptuous) (Nana: Where are you)
(หมี : ดูอร่อยนะ อีอี : ของกินเพียบเลย นานะ : นายอยู่ไหน)
Aunty.
อาเล็กครับ
How did Liu do
ปีนี้เสียวหลิ่ว
in his exams?
ผลสอบเป็นยังไงบ้างครับ
Don't mention it.
อย่าพูดถึงเลย
His English and literature
อังกฤษ จีน
are still so-so.
ยังพอทน
As for science
แต่วิทยาศาสตร์
and math,
คณิตศาสตร์
he's shown no improvement.
ไม่ได้เรื่องจริง ๆ
If you're free,
ถ้าว่าง
you should help him with his studies.
ช่วยสอนน้องหน่อยนะ
Aunty.
อาเล็กครับ
You see,
คือว่า
when it comes to math,
วิชาเลขเนี่ย
you must practice with a lot of questions.
ต้องหมั่นทำโจทย์
Exactly.
ใช่ ๆ
More quizzes for you.
ต้องทำโจทย์เยอะ ๆ
I was too lenient with you.
แม่ปล่อยตามใจเกินไปแล้ว
Not to worry, Aunty.
อาเล็ก ไม่ต้องห่วงครับ
Science runs deep in our family.
ตระกูลเรามีหัวด้านวิทยาศาสตร์
Work on more questions,
ทำโจทย์เยอะ ๆ
and it'll surely rise up.
รับรองทำฉลุยแน่
Exactly!
ถูกต้อง ๆ
Yeah.
ใช่ ๆ
Listen to your cousin.
ฟังที่พี่เขาพูดนะ
Liu.
เสียวหลิ่ว
Don't waste our genes.
อย่าให้กรรมพันธุ์ของตระกูลเราเสียของล่ะ
Keep it up.
สู้ ๆ
Alright.
มา มา ๆ
You can do better, Liu.
สู้ ๆ เสียวหลิ่ว
Keep it up!
สู้ ๆ
(Yu Tu)
(อวี๋ถู)
Jingjing,
พี่
it's for you.
โทรศัพท์
Hello?
ฮัลโหล
Hi there.
สวัสดีครับ
My sister is digging bamboo shoots.
พี่ผมกำลังขุดหน่อไม้
Just hang in there,
รอเดี๋ยวนะครับ
I'll give her the phone.
ผมเอาโทรศัพท์ไปให้พี่ก่อน
Alright, thanks.
ครับ ขอบคุณครับ
Who is it?
ใครโทรมา
Hello?
ฮัลโหล
It's me.
ฉันเอง
Yu Tu.
อวี๋ถู
You are digging bamboo shoots?
เธอขุดหน่อไม้อยู่เหรอ
You've gone to the mountains?
ขึ้นเขาไปแล้วใช่ไหม
I was about to ask you
เดิมฉันตั้งใจจะถามว่า
if you cared for a stroll
บ่ายนี้เธอว่างหรือเปล่า
with me this afternoon.
ออกไปเดินเล่นกัน
Yixing has changed a lot in the past two years.
สองปีมานี้อี๋ซิงเปลี่ยนไปเยอะเลย
The Dongjiu Lakeside is beautiful.
ริมทะเลสาบตงจิ่วสวยมากนะ
I'm at my grandma's in Hufu.
ตอนนี้ฉันอยู่บ้านยายที่ตำบลหูฟู่น่ะ
Tomorrow, I'll be at my grandpa's in the mountains.
พรุ่งนี้ต้องขึ้นเขาไปบ้านปู่
My schedule's full.
ไม่ว่างหรอก
Okay then.
โอเค
Have fun.
เที่ยวให้สนุกนะ
On the fourth day,
วันชูซื่อ
I will send you back to Shanghai.
ฉันจะไปส่งเธอกลับเซี่ยงไฮ้
We'll catch up then.
ไว้ค่อยว่ากัน
Bye.
แค่นี้นะ
Jingjing.
พี่
As an actress,
พวกนักแสดงอย่างพี่
you even pretended to be unknown when picking up the phone
จะรับโทรศัพท์ทีต้องลีลาเยอะขนาดนี้เลยเหรอ
You already knew who called,
เห็น ๆ อยู่ว่าใครโทรมา
yet you had to ask me about it.
ยังมาถามผมอีก
You even made me answer it.
แถมยังให้ผมรับแทน
He persisted on ringing me up,
ก็ฉันเห็นเขาไม่ยอมวางสายสักที
so I had you pick it up instead.
เสียงดังน่ารำคาญก็เลยให้นายรับแทนน่ะ
Couldn't you say I was not here?
นาย ทำไมไม่บอกไปว่าฉันไม่อยู่
Hurry up and dig.
ขุดสิ รีบขุดเลย
I want fried winter bamboo shoots with pickles for dinner tonight.
คืนนี้ฉันจะกินเกี่ยมฉ่ายผัดหน่อไม้
Dig up!
รีบขุดเลย
Stop fooling around.
เลิกเล่นได้แล้ว
I think there are some here.
ฉันว่าตรงนี้มี
You're the big sister. Anything you say.
พี่เป็นพี่ ผมเชื่อพี่
Mom.
แม่
I'm going for a walk.
ผมออกไปเดินเล่นนะ
Where do you go?
จะไปไหนลูก
A scenic spot.
เดินเล่นน่ะ
Yu Tu, I'm coming with you!
พี่ ผมไปด้วย
Get home early, okay?
พวกนายรีบกลับมานะ
Whose turn is it?
ตาใครแล้ว
(The girl whose photo you posted,)
(ผู้หญิงที่เธอส่งรูปมาคราวก่อน)
(have you found her a partner?)
(หาแฟนได้หรือยัง)
No, thanks.
ไม่เอาแล้ว ไม่เอาแล้ว
Another six-dots.
ตบด้วยไพ่หกท้งอีกแล้ว
Make that two six-dots.
หกท้งสองอันเลย
(Not yet.)
(อะไรจะเร็วขนาดนั้น)
(I haven't even seen her mother lately.)
(สองวันนี้ยังไม่เจอแม่เขาเลย)
(I haven't had time to tell you.)
(ฉันเลยยังไม่ได้บอก)
(Stop recommending her to others for now.)
(งั้นเธออย่ารอช้าเลย)
(Tomorrow night, you'll recommend her to Yu Tu)
(คืนพรุ่งนี้ตอนกินข้าว)
(over the dinner table.)
(พูดกับอวี๋ถูซะ)
Yu Tu,
พี่
we've been walking all afternoon.
เราเดินกันมาทั้งบ่ายแล้ว
Can we take a break?
ขอพักหน่อยได้ไหม
(10.05 km)
(ความเร็ว อัตราการเต้นของหัวใจ ระยะทาง)
It's already over 15,000 steps!
เดินมาหมื่นห้าพันกว่าก้าวแล้ว
That's it.
ไม่ได้
I'm stopping here.
ยังไงผมก็ไม่เดินแล้ว
I knew it.
รู้งี้
I might as well stay at home
ผมอยู่บ้าน
and chat with my girls.
แชทกับสาว ๆ ดีกว่า
(Qiao Jingjing)
(ตื่นหรือยัง แถวบ้านฉันมีร้านขายเต้าฮวย ชื่อดังในอี๋ซิงอยู่เจ้าหนึ่ง)
But no one chats with me.
แต่ไม่มีใครคุยกับฉันนี่
How about I teach you a few tricks
งั้นพี่ให้ค่าสอนผมสิ
for tuition fees?
ผมจะสอนเคล็ดลับให้
Let's go home.
กลับบ้านเถอะ
Can't you even take a break?
พักแป๊บไม่ได้หรือไง
Wait for me!
รอผมด้วย
We're on our way.
พวกเราออกเดินทางแล้ว
We'll be in Taihua
ประมาณครึ่งชั่วโมงได้
in about half an hour.
ถึงไท่หัวแล้ว
Yes,
ใช่
we'll spend the night.
นอนค้าง
Jingjing misses you too.
จิงจิงก็คิดถึงพวกคุณเหมือนกัน
Okay,
จ้ะ
bye.
บ๊ายบาย
Surprised to see me, grandma?
ตกใจไหมคะย่า
My granddaughter's so big now!
หลานสาวของย่า
Did you sleep well?
นอนพอไหมลูก
All right,
พอค่ะ
let's get us some breakfast.
กินข้าวเช้าก่อน
Sure.
ค่ะย่า
I made it just for you.
ย่าเตรียมไว้ให้แล้ว
Don't eat too much.
อย่ากินเยอะนะ
Once your aunt gets here in a moment,
เดี๋ยวอาก็มาถึงแล้ว
then we'll really dig in.
จะได้กินมื้อใหญ่พร้อมกัน
Okay.
ค่ะ
I made you your favorites.
ของที่หลานชอบทั้งนั้นเลย
That's enough, grandma.
พอแล้วค่ะย่า
Have some more.
กินเยอะ ๆ ลูก
Ignore your mother and eat more.
อย่าไปฟังแม่เขา กินเยอะ ๆ
My granddaughter loves zongzi so much,
บ๊ะจ่างที่หลานย่าชอบกิน
Let me peel it for you.
ย่าแกะให้นะ
(Yu Tu: When will you return to Yixing?)
ระวังลวกล่ะ
I'm fine.
ไม่กลัวค่ะ
This is your favorite.
นี่ของที่หลานชอบไง
It's made of purple rice.
ทำจากข้าวหอมนิล
Mom?
แม่
Why did you prepare so many dishes again?
ทำไมทำกับข้าวเยอะขนาดนี้ล่ะ
I have to hurry back in the afternoon.
ช่วงบ่ายต้องรีบกลับนะ
Says who?
ใครบอกแก
You won't leave before dinner.
กินข้าวเย็นก่อนแล้วค่อยกลับ
It's not like you visit us often.
หนึ่งปีโผล่มาไม่กี่ครั้ง
You people
แกนี่นะ
are always
รีบร้อนกลับ
on the go.
อะไรนักหนา
I have a date this afternoon.
บ่ายผมมีนัด
A mahjong date.
เล่นไพ่นกกระจอกน่ะ
You know what?
เอางี้ไหมแม่
How about you and dad
แม่กับพ่อ
come with us to our place?
ไปด้วยกันกับพวกผม
No!
ไม่ไป
I am carsick.
ฉันเมารถ
You and your mahjong all day long.
วัน ๆ เอาแต่เล่นไพ่นกกระจอก
You know what?
เอางี้
It's up to my granddaughter
พวกแกจะกลับตอนกี่โมง
when you may go.
ให้หลานสาวฉันตัดสินใจ
Jingjing,
จิงจิง
tell him.
ว่ามาลูก
Of course,
ก็ต้อง
we may leave only after dinner.
กินข้าวเย็นก่อนแล้วค่อยกลับสิคะ
See?
ถูกต้อง
I have to keep my grandparents company.
หนูต้องอยู่เป็นเพื่อนปู่กับย่าก่อน
You are so old,
แกอายุปูนนี้แล้ว
yet you lack Jingjing's sensibilities.
ยังไม่รู้ธรรมเนียมเท่าจิงจิงของเรา
Jingjing.
จิงจิง
I'll take you to harvest bamboo shoots later.
บ่ายนี้ปู่จะพาไปขุดหน่อไม้
Your maternal grandma's shoots
หน่อไม้บ้านยาย
aren't as sweet as ours.
หวานสู้ที่นี่ไม่ได้หรอก
We're not going back there.
ไม่กลับแล้วนะ
See how clever our granddaughter is.
หลานย่านี่เก่งจริง ๆ
You've got us a bumper harvest.
ขุดได้หน่อใหญ่เบ้อเริ่ม
That's a lot of shoots.
ขุดมาเยอะขนาดนี้เลยเหรอ
Okay, Jingjing.
เก่งนี่ จิงจิง
Your sister
พวกน้องสาวคุณ
has arrived at our house.
มารอพวกเรา
They're waiting for us.
อยู่ที่บ้านแล้วนะ
See, your daughter harvested all of these.
หน่อไม้พวกนี้ลูกสาวคุณเป็นคนขุด
You know what?
ฉันคิดว่า
Let's split them
แบ่งให้เสร็จซะตอนนี้
into fair portions
จัดให้คนละถุง
so our guests won't scrap over them.
พอไปถึงบ้านจะได้ไม่ต้องเหนื่อย
You're right.
ถูกต้อง
You know what?
เอางี้
Keep some for dad
เหลือไว้หน่อย
to dry them.
ให้พ่อผมเอาไว้ตากแห้ง
What?
ว่าไงนะ
Drying the winter bamboo shoots?
หน่อไม้ฤดูหนาวเอามาตากแห้ง
It's not worth it.
ไม่คุ้มหรอก
Take them away
เอาไปให้หมดนี่แหละ
and distribute them.
แบ่งญาติคนละถุง
Tell them,
บอกพวกเขาว่า
my granddaughter harvested these shoots.
หลานฉันเป็นคนขุด
To eat them is a blessing.
กินแล้วจะได้โชคดี
Yeah.
ใช่ค่ะ
What are you doing here?
จะมัวยืนหัวโด่อยู่ทำไม
Get down to work.
รีบมาช่วยกันสิ
Hurry up.
เร็ว ๆ เร็วหน่อย
Help us to pack these shoots.
ใส่ถุงซะ
Yeah.
ใช่ ๆ
Jingjing.
จิงจิง
You must eat well.
หลานต้องกินให้อิ่ม ๆ นะ
You get me?
ได้ยินไหมลูก
Yes, grandma.
ค่ะ
Get some good rest.
พักผ่อนให้เพียงพอ
It's so heavy.
สำคัญมากนะ
Drop by often when you're free.
ว่าง ๆ ก็แวะมาบ่อย ๆ นะ
Take care, grandma.
รักษาสุขภาพด้วยค่ะ ย่า
Dad, mom, let's go.
พ่อคะ แม่คะ พวกเรากลับก่อนนะคะ
Bye.
กลับแล้วแม่
Go to bed early.
รีบนอนนะ
- Bye, grandpa. - Remember
- กลับแล้วค่ะปู่ - อย่าลืมล่ะ
to call us once you get there.
ถึงบ้านแล้วโทรบอกด้วย
Okay.
ค่ะ
Hurry along now.
รีบไปเถอะ รีบไปเถอะ
Easy there.
ระวังนะ ระวัง
Grandpa, grandma, go in now.
ปู่กับย่ารีบเข้าบ้านเถอะค่ะ
It's freezing out here.
ข้างนอกหนาว เดี๋ยวจะไม่สบาย
Drive slowly.
ขับรถดี ๆ
Mom, go in.
แม่คะ เข้าบ้านเถอะ
Okay.
ค่ะแม่
(Jingjing, I'm back in Yixing.)
(จิงจิง ฉันกลับมาอี๋ซิงแล้ว)
(See you soon.)
(จะไปหาเธอเดี๋ยวนี้ล่ะ)
(I'm on my way back.)
(ฉันกำลังกลับ)
(Perhaps you can arrive a little later.)
(เธอมาดึกหน่อยแล้วกัน)
It's your turn.
รีบทิ้งมา
Hurry up.
เร็วสิ เร็ว
Nope.
ไม่เอาแล้ว
A pair of jacks.
ฉันมีคู่แจ็ค
Pair of two.
คู่สอง
Uncle's back.
ลุงเขย กลับมาแล้ว
Welcome back, Uncle!
สวัสดีครับ ลุงเขย
Look at me.
ดูหน้าไพ่ฉันสิ
What time is it now?
ดึกขนาดนี้แล้ว
How's the game?
เล่นกันสนุกไหม
Jingjing!
พี่
What the hell?
อะไรเนี่ย
My MVP!
เอ็มวีพีของฉัน
So nice!
สวยจริง ๆ
It's really troublesome
บ้านสามีฉันอยู่ต่างเมือง
that my in-laws stay in another place.
ไปลำบาก
Luckily you're in Changzhou.
ดีนะที่อยู่แค่ฉางโจว
Otherwise,
ไม่อย่างนั้น
I wouldn't be able
วันนี้ฉันคงกลับมา
to hang out with you today.
เล่นกับเธอไม่ทันแล้ว
That'd be
แบบนั้น
a huge loss for me.
ฉันคงเสียหายแย่
Thanks a lot!
งั้นฉันไม่เกรงใจแล้วนะ
You're so nice, Jingjing.
จิงจิงที่แสนดี
As a token of gratitude,
เพื่อตอบแทนเธอ
let's go hang out somewhere.
พวกเราออกไปเที่ยวกัน
Drink's on me.
ฉันเลี้ยงเครื่องดื่มเธอเอง
No, thanks.
อย่าเลยดีกว่า
It's seven o'clock.
หนึ่งทุ่มแล้วนะ
It's only seven o'clock.
แค่หนึ่งทุ่มเอง
That's still early, right?
ยังไม่ดึกสักหน่อย
Come on.
ไปกันเถอะ
We can go to Dongjiu.
พวกเราไปเดินเล่นที่ตงจิ่วกัน
It's been two years,
สองปีนี้
and Dongjiu has spruced up a lot.
ปรับปรุงซะสวยเลยแหละ
Dongjiu?
ตงจิ่วเหรอ
(I was about to ask you)
(เดิมฉันตั้งใจจะถามว่า)
(if you cared for a stroll)
(บ่ายนี้เธอว่างหรือเปล่า)
(with me this afternoon.)
(ออกไปเดินเล่นกัน)
(Yixing has changed a lot in the past two years.)
(สองปีมานี้อี๋ซิงเปลี่ยนไปเยอะเลย)
(The Dongjiu Lakeside is beautiful.)
(ริมทะเลสาบตงจิ่วสวยมากนะ)
There are so many,
ที่นั่นมี
very romantic,
ร้านกาแฟเก๋ ๆ
feel-good cafés over there.
ดูโรแมนติกเยอะแยะไปหมด
They come with private rooms.
แถมมีกั้นเป็นห้องเล็ก ๆ ด้วย
Okay then,
เอาสิ
let's go.
งั้นไปกันเถอะ
Let's take a lot of photos,
ไปถ่ายรูปเยอะ ๆ
enough to make a WeChat Moment.
เอามาโพสต์ลงโมเมนต์วีแชท
Alright,
ไป
let's go!
ไปกันเร็ว
Jingjing.
จิงจิง
Let me drive.
ฉันขับรถให้
Okay.
โอเค
Jingjing,
จิงจิง
Why on earth
ดูเธอซิ
did you leave your driver's license
ทำไมเอาใบขับขี่ของตัวเอง
at the back?
มาโยนไว้เบาะหลังล่ะ
Give it to me!
เอามา
(Yu Tu)
(อวี๋ถู)
♪I dreamed of starlight pulling the sleeves♪
♪ฉันฝันเห็นแสงดาวระยิบระยับ บนชายแขนเสื้อ♪
♪A white top covering the thin shoulders♪
♪ชุดสีขาว ปกคลุมหัวไหล่อันซูบเซียว♪
♪I have seen the wounds healed with each passing year♪
♪ฉันเห็นกาลเวลาเยียวยาบาดแผลได้♪
♪There will always be people running towards eternity♪
♪อย่างไรก็มีคนไล่ตามชั่วฟ้าดินสลาย♪
♪The bustling intersection♪
♪ท่ามกลางทางแยกผู้คนพลุกพล่าน♪
♪Looking back all of a sudden under the dim light♪
♪แสงไฟริบหรี่ เหลียวหลังมองไป♪
♪I loved your eyes looking at the starry sky♪
♪เคยรักเธอ มองไปยังดาวทอประกายบนฟากฟ้า นัยน์ตาที่สงบนิ่ง♪
♪And I loved the universe in your heart♪
♪ก็เคยรักเธอ ในใจฉันเธอคือทุกอย่าง ในจักรวาล♪
♪Time does not stop, remember the time that we failed to treasure♪
♪กาลเวลาไม่เคยหยุดรอ เก็บซ่อนความเสียใจในสิ่งที่ทำไปตลอดเวลา♪
♪I've dreamed of traveling around the planet♪
♪ฉันก็เคยคิดฝันท่องไปตามดวงดาว♪
♪Seeing the galaxy pass through the clouds♪
♪ผ่านมวลเมฆ ดูทางช้างเผือกที่หลั่งไหล♪
♪I looked at the hills with sorrow♪
♪ฉันเคยมองขุนเขาอย่างเศร้าหมอง♪
♪Will the exit of the dream lead to the end of the starry sky?♪
♪ทางออกแห่งฝัน อยู่ที่สุดขอบทะเลดาวหรือไม่♪
♪Looking back all of a sudden♪
♪เหลียวหลังมองไป♪
♪Which galaxy am I drifting on?♪
♪ฉันล่องลอยอยู่บนทะเลดาวสายไหนกัน♪
♪Looking into the distance, which of the stars are your eyes?♪
♪เฝ้ามองว่าดาวดวงไหนคือนัยน์ตาเธอ♪
♪It's out of reach, so dazzling and hard to get♪
♪ดาวระยิบระยับ เอื้อมไม่ถึงครอบครองไม่ได้♪
♪Time does not hold back, the spring and autumn in the passing time♪
♪กาลเวลาไม่รอใคร เมื่อเวลาผ่าน สรรพสิ่งก็เปลี่ยนไป อดีตจบสิ้นลง♪
♪The wind sings the song of freedom as I listen to the tenderness of time♪
♪สายลมขับร้องอิสรภาพ ฉันตั้งใจฟังความอ่อนโยนของกาลเวลา♪